<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The magistrates dignity and duty. Being a sermon preached on Octob. 30. 1653. at Pauls Church before the Right Honourable, Thomas Viner, Lord Major, and the aldermen of the city of London. Being the first sermon after his entrance into his majoralty. By William Spurstowe, D.D. minister of Gods Word at Hackney neere London.</title>
            <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E727_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93723)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E727[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The magistrates dignity and duty. Being a sermon preached on Octob. 30. 1653. at Pauls Church before the Right Honourable, Thomas Viner, Lord Major, and the aldermen of the city of London. Being the first sermon after his entrance into his majoralty. By William Spurstowe, D.D. minister of Gods Word at Hackney neere London.</title>
                  <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.C. for J. Rothwell, at the Fountain and Beare in Goldsmiths-row in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 24. 1653"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115733:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Magiſtrates DIGNITY AND DUTY.</p>
            <p>Being a SERMON preached on <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. 1653. at <hi>Pauls</hi> Church before the Right Honourable, THOMAS VINER, Lord Major, And the Aldermen of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being the firſt Sermon after his entrance into his Majoralty.</p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM SPURSTOWE, <hi>D. D.</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Hackney</hi> neere <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pium nomen impii reatus. <hi>Salv.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Job 29. 14, 15.</bibl>
            <q>I put on righteouſneſs, and it cloathed me: my judgement was as a Robe and a Diadem. I was eyes to the blinde, and feet was I to the lame.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>J. Rothwell,</hi> at the Fountain and Beare in <hi>Goldſmiths-row</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1654</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115733:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, THOMAS VINER, Lord Major of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>INſtead of an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> I am ſo far neceſſitated, as to preſent You wth an <hi>Apology;</hi> to doe my ſelfe ſo much right as to remove any ſuſpition of backwardneſs to fulfill Your commands, which the ſlowneſſe of this Sermon in its motion towards You might juſtly beget. It hath ſome time ſince been called for by your Honours order; and hath ſtuck longer in the birth then was meet it ſhould, by reaſon of ſome intervening occaſions which have bin an hindrance unto the more early publiſhing of it: Elſe my willingneſſe to perform Your pleaſure might have been ſooner viſible, but not more reall then now it is. But I hope it is neither too late to tender this ſmall piece as an acknowledgment of my obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Your Honour for Your many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours:
<pb facs="tcp:115733:3"/> Nor yet to revive any affections which by the bleſſing of God upon it might be ſtirring in the preaching of it; ſo as to make them not to be abortive, or as untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly births that never come to a perfection. My deſires are that You, and that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bench, in which Your ſelfe at preſent have the Chair, may all be as Trees laden with diverſity of Graces: Such as a certain Hiſtorian ſtiles <hi>Marcianus</hi> the Emperour, whom he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Trees not having onely the <hi>leaves</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> but the <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi> And becauſe that in moſt of You the <hi>Almond-tree</hi> doth flouriſh, and that <hi>Age</hi> hath made You more then <hi>gray;</hi> and that <hi>Death</hi> may and will ere long make You <hi>pale;</hi> that You may be like the trees planted in the houſe of God, which bring forth fruit in their old age, and are both fat and flouriſhing: that ſo ſerving Your Generation in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, You may be rewarded with the rich bleſſings of life and glory. And this is the prayer of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours in all Chriſtian ſervice, WILLIAM SPURSTOWE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115733:3"/>
            <head>THE MAGISTRATES DIGNITY and DUTY.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a SERMON preached on <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. 1653. at <hi>Pauls</hi> Church before the Right Honourable, the Lord Major and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 82. 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty;</hi> (Or in the aſſembly of the gods.) <hi>He judgeth among the gods;</hi> (Or, in the midſt he will judge the gods.)</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Medalls do receive their worth, and eſteeme from the impreſſion and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which is put upon them, ſo do aſſemblies derive their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115733:4"/> and luſtre from the perſons which do conſtitute and make them up.</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſpeakes of two kinds of Aſſemblies; the one of which it brands with infamy, and the other it dignifies with titles of praiſe. There is <hi>Coetus malignantium,</hi> an Aſſembly of wicked and violent perſons, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 22. 16. whoſe deſignes doe breath forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but cruelty; and in their counſels <hi>David</hi> makes it a marke of the bleſſed man not to ſtand. There is <hi>Coetus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicatorum</hi> an Aſſembly of corrupt, and treacherous perſons; and above this the Prophet prefers a barren and ſolitary deſert; <hi>O that I had in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſse the lodging place of wayfairing men, that I might leave my people, and goe from them, for they be all adulterers, an Aſſembly of treacherous men. Jer.</hi> 9, 2. There is <hi>Coetus illicitus,</hi> An unlawful and tumultuous Aſſembly <hi>Acts 19. 40. We are in danger to be called in queſtion for this dayes uprore, there being no cauſe whereby we may give an account of this concourſe,</hi> and unto this no ſober and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115733:4"/> prudent man will joyne himſelf. There is an Aſſembly which though it be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne, is yet ſo prophane, that God will not ſmell in it. <hi>Amos.</hi> 5. 21.</p>
            <p>But there are alſo aſſemblies that are as glorious, as theſe are inglorious; that beare upon them the ſtamp of Majeſty, as theſe doe of ignominy. There is the general aſſembly of the firſtborn, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12, 23, in which all the heirs of glory ſhall be gathered together, and put into the full poſſeſſion of that inheritance which is immortal, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. There are the aſſemblies of the Saints on earth, in which the order and beauty is ſuch, as that it drawes an awfull reſpect from the beholders of them; <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſembly of the Saints: and to be had in reverence of all thoſe that are about him, Pſal.</hi> 89. 7. There is an aſſembly in which the beames of Diety doe ſhine ſo bright, as that it appeares to be rather a convention of Gods then of men, of which we may truly ſay, what they of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> did concerning <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115733:5"/> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> that <hi>the gods are come downe to us in the likeneſſe of men, Acts</hi> 14. 11. And ſuch is the aſſembly, which is in the Text, in which as in a well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered aſſembly you have two parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>perſons</hi> that doe conſtitute and make it up: and they are ſuch, as that the name of God is beſtowed upon them; but without any addition of his attributes, and divine perfections. They are gods, but not immortal, not onely wiſe, not unlimited in their Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Wil. Things are not juſt becauſe they will them; but becauſe things are juſt, therefore they ought to wil, and to enjoyn them; Juſtice is the rule of their will, and not their will the rule of Juſtice,</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Preſident</hi> who is over, and above the aſſembly of gods. And he is ſuch a perſon, who though he ſtand among them, is yet altogether diſtinct from them both in his nature, and in his power. They are <hi>Elohim,</hi> gods by office, and by patent. He is <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> god by his eſſence and being.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115733:5"/> They are his Vice-royes to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the affaires of men on earth, which is his footſtoole, and he is their abſolute Soveraigne, to whom they muſt give a juſt account in heaven. He is deſcribed, and ſet forth by two of his divine properties and perfections.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the property of his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence and his omniſcience. <hi>God ſtandeth in the congregation of the mighty.</hi> There is no aſſembly, or meeting of the earthly Dieties, but God is preſent at it, and ſtands among them. And he ſtands not like an Idol or <hi>Dagon,</hi> which neither heares nor obſerves any thing that is done; but he ſtands marking and weighing all their tranſactions from the beginning to the end. His eye beholds what they do, his eare heares what they ſpeak, his hand writes downe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which they pronounce. Oh then how circumſpect had they need to be, who have ſuch a ſtrict and ſevere obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of their actions alwayes preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them!</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the property of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115733:6"/> Juſtice, and power. <hi>He judgeth among the gods.</hi> When they judge, and decree righteous things, then he judgeth with them, and ratifies the edicts, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they make; but when they <hi>turne judgement to wormewood, and leave off righteouſneſſe in the earth, Amos.</hi> 5. 7. then he judgeth the gods themſelves, then in the <hi>midſt</hi> or <hi>openly</hi> in the ſight of others, <hi>he breaketh in pieces mighty men without number, and ſets others in their ſtead, Job.</hi> 34. 24. 26.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt part, viz. the <hi>perſons</hi> which do make up and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the ſolemne meeting, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention which the Text ſpeaketh of. And I ſhall make it the principal drift of my preſent taske to ſpeak of them, and to them. The ſecond part I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch upon by way of application, and enforcement to move thoſe who are called gods, to behave and carry themſelves like gods, doing nothing unworthy of ſo great a name. <hi>Monſtroſa res eſt gradus ſummus &amp; animus infimus, ſedes prima &amp; vita ima.</hi> A high ſeat and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115733:6"/> a baſe minde, a principal place, and a common behaviour, is a thing not only unſightly but deformed and monſtrous, as <hi>Bernard</hi> tells his <hi>Eugenius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of the firſt part, I ſhall propound for the explication of it three particulars,</p>
            <p>Firſt, who they be that are called gods. It is a title that is not vulgar, and will not fit every perſon, no more then a Crown will ſuit with every head, or a Scepter with every hand. Select and choiſe perſons they muſt needs be, and ſuch as beare a more lively reſemblance of God then others, who have his own name conferred upon them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew how they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are, nor may be called gods.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what thoſe reſpects are, in which they may be juſtly ſtiled gods, for it is not a title without reality. He that hath impoſed upon them his name, hath alſo imparted unto them his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>Firſt, who they be that are called gods. They to whom this high appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115733:7"/> is given have alſo many other names of eminency beſtowed upon them in the Scripture. They are called <hi>Vertices populi,</hi> the <hi>Heads of the people, Numb.</hi> 10. 4. Such as are as far above the common ranke of men in their worth, as <hi>Saul</hi> was above the people in ſtature, who when he ſtood among the people, was higher then any of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the ſhoulders and upwards. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 23. They are <hi>Scuta terrae,</hi> ſhields of the earth; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. 9. which among all military inſtruments were the moſt honourable, and were wont to be preſerved with the greater care, and adorned with the greateſt coſt. They are <hi>Saviours</hi> or <hi>deliverers, Judg.</hi> 3. 9. which is a word of that Emphaſis, as that <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ita magnum eſt, ut unto verbo exprimi non poſſit.</hi> It is ſo great, as no one word can expreſſe the force of it. They are called <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> or <hi>Binders, Job. 34. 17. Shall he that hateth right, governe?</hi> or as it is in the Hebrew, <hi>binde.</hi> It is their office <hi>juſtiſſimas facere luxationum compoſitiones,</hi> to heale Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115733:7"/> in a State, and to ſet every bone in its juſt place. They are <hi>foundations, Pſal.</hi> 82. 6. upon the ſtrength of which the weight of the whole building ſtands, and is preſerved from ruine and ſinking. <hi>If the foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous doe?</hi> Pſal. 11. 2. They are <hi>Fathers,</hi> Iſa. 49. 23. which is a name, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes both <hi>power</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe;</hi> Who hath more power over his child then a father, to doe with him as he pleaſeth? and who hath more bowels, to do every thing for him which he deſireth? All theſe and many other more titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doth the Scripture heape upon thoſe perſons, who in the Text are called <hi>Gods,</hi> which is of all the greateſt, and the higheſt. And they who are here dignified with the name of gods, are no other, then the bench and ſeat of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Magiſtracy; to whom he hath given power and authority by a charter from Heaven, to order and regulate the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the ſonnes of men on earth; and to prevent all that confuſion and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115733:8"/> ruine, which would inevitably fall out, if every man ſhould be left to doe what ever is right in his own eyes. Now the end that God hath ſet ſo many ſacred ſignatures, and marks of honour upon their perſons, is;</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they may the better read their <hi>duty,</hi> and know how to carry themſelves in the diſcharge of that great truſt which is repoſed in them. It is not that <hi>Haman</hi> like they ſhould ſwel with pride, and make no other uſe of their power, then to execute their luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſſions of wrath, and revenge upon every one that <hi>Mordecai</hi> like can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtoop and bow, to break Gods lawes, to fulfill their imperious wills, that are vitiated with corrupt and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid humours. Such a temper is more fit for thoſe that are <hi>Nimrods,</hi> hunters of men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 9. then for them that are <hi>nurſing-fathers,</hi> Iſa. 49. 23. For ſuch as are <hi>Flagella dei,</hi> the ſcourges of God, (as <hi>Attila</hi> was wont to be called) that are permitted by him to chaſtiſe and afflict a people for their ſins; then for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115733:8"/> ſuch that are ordained <hi>Miniſtri dei,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God for the good and benefit of them over whom they rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the end is, that thereby God might implant in the minds of men an awfull reverence towards their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and a willingneſſe to yeild obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their juſt commands. If we conſider how like unto the Sea the multitude is in its motions, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blaſt of winde doth diſturbe, and makes to become tempeſtuous; and how like they are in their paſſions unto tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which every ſparke that falls doth kindle and ſet on fire; Is it not a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that oftentimes the preſence of one, or a few Magiſtrates ſhould not onely bridle their fury, but alſo calme it, and allay it? that one word from their mouthes ſhould extinguiſh the fire of ſedition, that is ready to break forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a flame? as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did the mutiny of his whole army, onely by ſaying, <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</hi> How can all this be, but that God himſelf hath imprinted his own name
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115733:9"/> upon Magiſtracy, and by their ſeveral titles, as by ſo many golden letters hath made it to be read and ſeen by every eye, that there is a divine conſtitution under an humane perſon?</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular propounded is, to ſhew in what reſpects Magiſtrates are not to be eſteemed gods. For as there are ſundry reſpects in which they truly may, and ought to be reputed gods; yet there are divers others alſo, in which they ought not to be called gods. Foure I ſhall touch upon, though more may eaſily be added to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are <hi>Nuncupative</hi> gods, by their titles and appellations; but they are not gods in their being and eſſence. They are neither <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> gods in their ſubſtance or nature, or in the leaſt manner like un to God in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The divinity is not ſtamp't upon their perſons; but upon their office. Their divine conſtitution doth not change their native condition: there is a wide difference between the lofty <hi>Cedar</hi> that grows in the mountaines, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115733:9"/> the low <hi>Myrtle</hi> that is in the valley; but yet they are both but vegetative be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and have the earth as their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon parent: So between the greateſt <hi>Monarch</hi> and the meaneſt <hi>peaſant</hi> there is a vaſt diſproportion, but yet the originall and principles of their being are the ſame. What the oppreſſed Jewes ſpake, that were in bondage to their brethren, <hi>Our fleſh is as the fleſh of our brethren, our children as their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Nehem. 5. 5. may be truly ſaid of all earthly gods, their off-ſpring is as the off-ſpring of other men, and their own fleſh, as the fleſh of others; their diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are as many, their paines as bitter, their life as uncertaine, their death as certaine. <hi>Pares naſcuntur, pares mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur;</hi> in the <hi>womb,</hi> and in the <hi>tombe</hi> they are all alike. All their excellency ariſeth from their office, and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates to their perſons ſuch an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reverence, as that men may not deſpiſe them, as the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> did <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 10. 27. or reproach them, as <hi>Shemei</hi> did <hi>David, 2 Sam.</hi> 16. 7,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115733:10"/> God himſelfe hath ſtrictly forbidden it, <hi>Exod. 22. 28. Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods of thy people.</hi> They are to have <hi>oſculum oris,</hi> the kiſſe of the mouth, to teſtifie the reverence of the outward man; thus <hi>Samuel</hi> kiſſed <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 10. 1. they are to have <hi>vota cordis,</hi> the prayers of the heart, to evidence the affection of the inward man; and this the Apoſtle enjoynes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are not Gods by way of <hi>Ironie,</hi> and deriſion, as the Idols of the Heathen in Scripture are called gods, or as the Gluttons belly is called his god, or as the covetous mans mony is ſaid to be his god. This honourable title God doth not give to Magiſtracy, as the Souldiers did the name of a King unto our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 29. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raying him, Crowning him, bowing the knee unto him, not to worſhip him, but to ſcorne him. God is more jealous of his name, then to give it for any ſuch purpoſes. And yet in thefe licentious times, wherein the worſt of men take a liberty both of ſpeaking, and doing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115733:10"/> what they pleaſe, how is the Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Magiſtracy trampled upon with the foot of Pride, and Scorn? How is it with loud clamours cryed down, as if it were a thing altogether uſeleſs, and unprofitable; like to ſome old heartleſs and uſeleſs drug, that hath loſt all its vertue and efficacy? Yea, how is it look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by many, as a powerful obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and hindrance unto the growth of Chriſts Kingdom, and the enjoyment of thoſe glorious liberties, which beſt ſute Goſpel times, and therefore they think it fit that it be wholly removed, and dealt with, as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did with the brazen ſerpent, which being no more an ordinance, but an Idol, he brake it in pieces, and called it, <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> 2 Kings 18. 4. But if there were not very ſtrange <hi>ſuffuſions</hi> upon the eye of theſe mens reaſon, Magiſtracy which is in it ſelfe a ſtraight and right object, could never appeare to be ſo crooked, as to be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med rather a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling,</hi> then a <hi>corner-ſtone</hi> to ſupport the building; to be an Idol to be broken, rather then an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115733:11"/> 
               <hi>inſtitution</hi> to be preſerved. For who can be, either to ſtorie common, or ſacred, ſo great a ſtranger, as not to know with what innumerable evils that Monſter of <hi>Anarchie</hi> hath always been attended? If we look into the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> wee ſhall finde that when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or Ruler that might put them unto ſhame, there was groſs Idolatry ſet up in the <hi>ſeventeenth Chapter;</hi> there was Violence, Rapine, together with ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood exerciſed in the <hi>eighteenth Chapter,</hi> there was Uncleanneſs, and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhings unto death in the <hi>ninteenth Chapter.</hi> If you look into the late <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> of <hi>Germanie,</hi> wee may finde that it was the ſcene where theſe and ſuch like evils were acted over again with greater rage and fury, when thoſe who were profeſſed enemies to Government and Authority had got power into their hands. And can we at home ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to gather Grapes of theſe Thornes, or Figs of theſe Thiſtles? The <hi>Perſians</hi> had anciently a cuſtome, that when their chiefe Ruler dyed, there ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115733:11"/> be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a lawleſneſſe, and liberty for five daies after, that every one might doe without controlle what he pleaſed: Now in this ſhort intervall of government, there were ſuch rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, murthers, violences of all kinds committed by the headleſſe multitude; as that they were exceeding glad that government ſhould take place again. And ſhould there be but ſuch a liberty amongſt us but for the ſpace of ſo many houres (which God forbid) many that are not now ſenſible of the benefit of Magiſtracy, would if they had not put off humanity, quickly change their opinion, and as ſtrongly deſire it, and wiſh for it, as before they loathed and deſpiſed it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Magiſtrates are not gods <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to equality of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and dignity. The bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſons in the Trinity, though they have an order among them; yet they have no priority or poſteriority; though they be diſtinct ſubſiſtences, yet they have an unity of eſſence: they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115733:12"/> are all equally God, and alike infinite in their power, wiſdome, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But ſo it is not with the earthly gods; their power, their honour, their wiſdome, are not equall or alike in all; though they be as ſo many lines that derive their being from one common center; yet they do not equally ſtretch themſelves towards the ſame circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Some are like Stars of the firſt magnitude, that move in an higher orbe; others are as Stars of a leſſe magnitude, that have their motions in a narrower and lower ſphere. Some have <hi>poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vitae &amp; necis,</hi> the power of life and death; others have onely the power of cuſtody, and of inflicting leſſer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and cenſures. Some are as the fountaines of authority, and others are as the rivulets that flow from them. This diſtinction the Scripture it ſelfe makes, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. when it exhorts believers to yield ſubmiſſion to every ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King, as ſupreme, or unto other Governours that are ſent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115733:12"/> by him. But as Gold hath the name of Gold when it is in the thin leafe, as well as when it is in the maſſie wedge: ſo are the loweſt Judicatories an aſſembly of gods, as well as the higheſt. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaking of Magiſtrates, reſembles thoſe that are of the <hi>firſt ranke,</hi> unto pictures that are drawn from head to feet; the <hi>middle ſort,</hi> unto ſuch pictures as are drawn no further then the girdle; &amp; the <hi>loweſt,</hi> to ſuch as goe no further then to the neck or ſhoulders. But all have the name of gods; as the ſmalleſt penny beares upon it the image of the Prince, as well as the greateſt piece, though in a leſſe character and compaſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they are not gods in regard of the ultimate end of their office, or of their actings in it. God, as he is the fountaine of all being; ſo is he the end of all being. As all things are of him, and from him; ſo muſt all things be for him, and to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 33. He can have no other center of his actions, then his hononr and glory, no more then he can have any cauſes of his being beſides
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115733:13"/> himſelfe. As he is <hi>Alpha,</hi> ſo he muſt be <hi>Omega.</hi> In this reſpect no Magiſtrate, or Aſſembly of gods can be like unto God; becauſe they are his Miniſters, whom he hath ordained for the good of others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. They are as lamps that ſpend and waſte themſelves to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten others. They are as the eyes in the body, which look not upon themſelves; but are exerciſed in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſafety of the leaſt member. And when any Magiſtrate ceaſeth thus to act, he is then both moſt unlike God, and moſt unworthy of the high Name and Title of a god. A ſelf-ſeeking Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is one of the worſt of plagues &amp; judgements that can befall a people; he is as a gangreene in the head, which brings both a more ſpeedy and a more certain ruine, then if it were in ſome inferiour and leſſe Noble part of the body. He is not then a <hi>Shepheard</hi> to defend the innocent ſheep, that run un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for protection; but a <hi>wolfe,</hi> to worry and devoure them. He is not then an <hi>Olive-tree,</hi> that drops fatneſſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115733:13"/> but a <hi>Bramble,</hi> from which fire comes that burnes up and conſumes the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> He is not a <hi>Sunne,</hi> that is the publique ſervant of light unto the world, and ſhines not for it ſelfe, but others; but a <hi>Comet</hi> that ſcatters abroad malignant vapours, and by its blazing bodes nothing but ruine. He is not in the politique body as a ſanguifying <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> in the body naturall, that ſends forth nouriſhment to every member, and fils every veine with blood; but as an ill and diſtempered <hi>Spleen,</hi> that robs the whole of its due nutriment, to make it ſelfe great, above what is convenient for its own welfare, and the good of every other part. And oh! that we had no better evidences then jealouſies, and preſumptions, that many among us, who are called by the name of gods, might be ſaid to be ſelf-ſeeking gods; that many who ſit in publique places were not byaſſed with private reſpects; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it more in their deſignes, and in their thoughts, how to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great, then how to make the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115733:14"/> proſperous, by cauſing <hi>judgement to roll down as waters, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtream. Amos.</hi> 5. 24. The learned <hi>Tully</hi> who was a zealous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot, and lover of his country, did wiſh two wiſhes, though hee never ſaw ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them affected: the one was, that he might ſee <hi>Rome</hi> ſetled in its juſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: the other was, that he might ſee every mans eſtate proportionable to his affection and love unto the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique. And ſurely if this wiſh might take place in our times, I believe the <hi>purſes</hi> of many would be more empty, and the <hi>coffers</hi> of the State would be more full.</p>
            <p>The third particular propounded is, to ſhew how lawfull Magiſtrates are called gods. For it is not a naked ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which conveyeth nothing of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and reality with it. They are not gods, as an Herauld is a King at Armes, who hath onely the name of a King, but nothing of the dignity or Revenues of a King. Hee who hath given this name of excellency unto them, hath derived an anſwerable
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115733:14"/> power and authority, in regard of which they may be juſtly called gods, and that in a three-fold reſpect.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are gods by way of <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi> as they ſtand in his ſtead, and have the managing of all affaires which concerne his ſoveraignty and glory. <hi>The Earth is the Lords, Pſal.</hi> 24. 1. and to him whoſe the earth is, doth all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and dominion belong, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 11. Now becauſe men cannot beare the immediate diſpenſations of God, no more then the Iſraelites could his giving of the Law from the Mount, but cryed out unto <hi>Moſes, ſpeake thou with us, and we will heare; but let not God ſpeak with us, leſt we dye, Exod.</hi> 20. 19. Therefore hath God been pleaſed to convey his power, juſtice, and wiſdome by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and inſtitution of Magiſtracy; but yet after ſuch a manner and way, as that all the tranſactions of juſtice, and all the enſignes of power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority are truly his, and not theirs. The <hi>Lawes</hi> which they rule by are his, and not theirs; <hi>The legiſlative</hi> power is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115733:15"/> not theirs, but onely the <hi>executive</hi> power. <hi>There is one law-giver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy, James</hi> 4. 12. The <hi>Throne</hi> on which they ſit is Gods Throne, 1 <hi>Chron. 29. 23. Solomon ſate on the throne oſ the Lord.</hi> The <hi>Scepter</hi> which they bear in their hand it is Gods Scepter, Exod. 4. 20. <hi>Moſes had the rod of God in his hand. The judgement</hi> which they give is Gods judgement, <hi>Deut. 1. 17. You ſhall not be afraid of the face of man, for the judgement is Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they are gods in reſpect of that peculiar <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>dignity</hi> which is put upon them above others. They are <hi>all ſons of the moſt high, Pſal.</hi> 82. 6. But how? Not by <hi>Generation;</hi> ſo Chriſt is the onely Beloved, and the onely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God. Not by <hi>Adoption;</hi> ſo Believers onely are called the ſons of God, being by a ſpiritual conformity unto him made like unto him, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Image of God upon them as a childe doth of his Father. But they are ſons of God by way of <hi>Eminency:</hi> their office and power being above and over
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115733:15"/> all others, as being his <hi>Deputies, &amp; Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents:</hi> their perſons being more ſacred, as being his <hi>Anointed</hi> ones: their relation to him being more ſingular and ſpeciall; as being in a more immediate ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination unto God then others are. Now this title of <hi>ſonnes,</hi> God gives unto Magiſtrates, that he might the better draw and win men to yeild a juſt ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; obedience unto them. The ſons of great Perſonages have reſpects &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances given to them, which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied unto their ſervants; when the one are ſlighted, the other uſually are regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The Lord of the Vineyard, when his ſervants were beaten and killed by the husband-men to whom he ſent them: did yet expect, that their beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and carriage to his Son would have been far otherwiſe, and upon that ground he ſent him, ſaying, <hi>they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence my ſon,</hi> Mat. 21. 37. But when violence was done unto him, then meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to offer peace are no more ſent, but an Army to deſtroy. And ſo when men deſpiſe dignities, &amp; lightly eſteem
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115733:16"/> the ſonnes of the moſt high, whom God would have to be honoured, <hi>A cruell meſsenger ſhall be ſent againſt them,</hi> Prov. 17. 11.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are gods in reſpect of their <hi>Call</hi> and miſſion. <hi>He called them gods unto whom the word came,</hi> John 10. 35. They are not onely ſuffered by him, but ſent of him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18. When men become Rulers onely by Gods permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; then the worſt of men doe get into the Throne of Soveraignty and power, being ſuffered by God to break Nations in pieces with a Rod of Iron, and not to govern them with a golden Scepter. <hi>Cedrenus</hi> tels a ſtory, that when <hi>Phocas</hi> the Paracide had made his way to the Empire, by the blood of <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his predeceſſour, there was a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man that did in an expoſtulatory manner complaine to God, ſaying, Lord wherefore haſt thou made this man Emperour? And an anſwer was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God unto him, <hi>quoniam non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni pejorem.</hi> Becauſe I have not found a worſe. It ſeemes the ſinnes of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115733:16"/> Roman State were grown to ſuch an height, that if God could have found out a worſe inſtrument then <hi>Phocas</hi> to afflict them, they ſhould have had him to ſit at the helme of government. But when God doth by his Warrant and Commiſſion call men unto the office of Magiſtracy, he chuſeth men that are fit and meet to ſit in that Aſſembly of gods, over which he is Preſident. It was <hi>Hirams</hi> expreſſion to <hi>Solomon, Becauſe the Lord loved his people, therefore hath he made thee to be King over them; 2 Chron.</hi> 2. 11. Now this <hi>Call</hi> of God, whereby any have Authority and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er given unto them, is either extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or ordinary: the one is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate from God, and thus <hi>Saul, David, Solomon,</hi> were all ſet upon the Throne of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but this Call is not now to be expected. The other is mediate; which is by the deſignation and appointment of man. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> did by the adviſe of <hi>Jethro,</hi> ſelect and chuſe out of the people ſuch perſons as were endued with qualifications fit for Magiſtracy,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115733:17"/> to be Rulers over the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 15. And this is the Call which is uſuall and conſtant, which being after a regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and due manner performed, becomes the Call of God. But a Call there muſt be, to give a title to Magiſtracy: or elſe it is not an Authority, but an uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; not a miſſion, by Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but a permiſſion by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. As to the weighty Office of the Miniſtery, no man may preſume to entitle himſelfe; or to runne unleſſe he be ſent, without being an intruder: No more may any man take the liberty to cloath himſelfe with the robes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, and to ſit in the aſſembly of the gods, without a juſt and lawful Call thereunto.</p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed the ſeverall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars that were propounded for the explication of the firſt branch of the Text; by ſhewing who they are, that are ſtiled an Aſſembly of Gods: And in what reſpect <hi>Negatively,</hi> they are not Gods: <hi>Poſitively,</hi> how they are, and juſtly may be honoured with the name
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115733:17"/> and title of Gods. The few ſands of time that are not yet runne, I ſhall allot for the application.</p>
            <p>And are Magiſtrates Gods? Oh! then how many are there, that in the Aſſembly of gods, are not <hi>Starres,</hi> but <hi>Spots:</hi> who are as unworthy to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>gods,</hi> as the duſt and dark earth to be a ſhining <hi>Planet.</hi> They are honoured with the name; but they doe nothing that may honour the Office to which they are called. Some there be that are <hi>Idol-gods,</hi> which have eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not, hands and handle not; that are as uſeleſſe in their places, as Images are in Churches. Others there be, to whom this name can no otherwiſe agree, then by an <hi>Antiphraſis,</hi> or contrariety, like <hi>Diogenes</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; <hi>Manes, à manendo,</hi> becauſe he was every other while running away; ſo they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, gods becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, Atheiſts both in opinion and practice; of the ſame ſtamp with the unjuſt Judge, who neither feared God, nor regarded man, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 2. Some
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115733:18"/> there be that are Gluttons and <hi>Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods,</hi> who eate of the fat, and drink of the ſweet, which great and high places afford; but altogether neglect the weighty things of judgement, mercy, and truth; that waſte not onely the morning, but the day in the ſenſuall pleaſures of the pallate; and thereby bring a woe upon the Land where they are Rulers, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 16. And are there not others that are haughty and <hi>proud gods,</hi> that delight to imitate God in his lightning and thunder: in making men to tremble at their threanings, and to dread every frown that ſits upon their brow; but love not to be like him in the darting out the amiable beams of goodneſſe, and gentleneſſe? Are not others <hi>Avaritious gods,</hi> who ſet their hearts upon nothing but the encreaſe of riches; making themſelves great not onely by the ſweat, but by the blood of many, whom they by oppreſſion have ſqueezed and drained, as grapes that are trodden in the Wine-preſſe! O what irreconcileable contradictions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115733:18"/> are theſe! to be a God, and yet an Idol; a God, and yet an Atheiſt, a Glutton: a God, but yet proud, covetous. Who ever heard of ſuch gods, unleſſe it were among the Heathen, where the matchleſſe impiety of many perſons was the chiefe ground of their being made and reputed gods; as may appeare by the impure ſtories which themſelves doe report of them? But, O let it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> or publiſhed in <hi>Askelon,</hi> that amongſt Chriſtians, that profeſſe not onely Religion, but a Reformation, thoſe are honoured with the ſacred title of gods, who have by their impure lives made a forfeiture of the name of men. The looſe walking of many Chriſtians was (as <hi>Salvian</hi> complaines) made by the Pagans the reproach of Chriſt himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>Si Chriſtus ſancta docuiſſet, Chriſtiani ſanctè vixiſſent.</hi> If Chriſt had taught holy doctrine, ſurely his followers had lead better lives. But, O let there not be an occaſion and advantage given for any to take up unworthy thoughts of God,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115733:19"/> who wils no wickedneſſe, ſo as to judge him to allow and favour prophaneneſſe, injuſtice oppreſſion, becauſe that they who are called gods doe abound in the practice of thoſe and ſuch like ſinnes. And to this end it concerns thoſe who have a power either to elect, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme any perſon in the office of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, to be circumſpect whom they take into the Aſſembly of the Gods, that ſo no diſhonour reflect upon God, whoſe name they beare; or contempt be poured forth upon the office, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it vile, by the foule enormities of thoſe that are betruſted with it. The irreligious behaviour of <hi>Eli</hi> his ſonnes, made the offering of the Lord to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 17. And ſo doth the impiety of Magiſtrates make Magiſtracy it ſelfe to become deſpicable in the eyes of the people.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Application directs it ſelfe to you, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> and to thoſe that are Aſſeſſors with you on the bench of Judicature; that you would doe worthily in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhew
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115733:19"/> your ſelves no other then an Aſſembly of Gods, by executing judgement, and working righteouſneſſe, which are the great workes by which God is known, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 16. Without you, what are the Laws, but <hi>leges cadaveroſoe,</hi> liveleſſe and unactive carcaſſes, as inſtruments with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the touch of a skilfull hand, that make no melody, as Vines that creep along upon the ground, and become unfruitfull for want of ſupport? What are they, but as the Letter without the Spirit, which profiteth not? It is you alone that muſt make them to live, to beare fruit, and to be uſefull for the good of this great City, and thoſe over whom you rule. I confeſſe indeed, that the times into which you are caſt, are full of difficulty; and ſuch of which we may ſay, as <hi>Livie</hi> ſometime did of the Roman State, <hi>Nec remedia poſſumus ferre, nec vitia;</hi> that we can neither beare our medicines, nor yet our mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: we groan under the one; and yet are impatient of the other. But yet, however let me beſeech you, to doe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115733:20"/> what in you lies, to keep Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Religion it ſelfe, from an irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable ſhipwrack; and if you <hi>periſh</hi> in your <hi>work,</hi> yet will you <hi>live</hi> in your <hi>name. In naufragio laudandus eſt Rector, quem mare obruit clavum tenentem.</hi> That Pilot dies nobly, who (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) periſheth in the ſtorm with the Helme in his hand. Endeavour to make good thoſe titles of eminency with which God hath honoured you above others; and to be as much above them in <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as you are above them in <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> You are <hi>Mountaines, Micah</hi> 6. 2. O then be like the mountaines of Myrrhe and Frankincenſe, which ſend forth a ſweet ſmell, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 6. and not like thoſe of <hi>Mizpah</hi> and <hi>Tabor,</hi> upon which ſnares and nets are ſpread, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5. 1. You are <hi>Healers, Iſai.</hi> 3. 7. be then as compaſſionate Chirurgeons, that mind more the welfare of their Patient, then their profit. You are <hi>Leaders, Iſai.</hi> 9. 16. be then neither <hi>blind Guides,</hi> nor <hi>falſe Guides,</hi> to ſeduce into the paths of errour, or to lead into the pit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115733:20"/> of deſtruction. You are <hi>Nurſing-fathers, Iſai.</hi> 49. 23. be not then <hi>Egyptian task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters,</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſigh bitterly under their cruell bondage. In one word, you are <hi>Gods,</hi> which is a title <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount,</hi> a name that excels every other name; O therefore let not this pious name be joyned to a godleſſe life. As ye are gods, ſo be like God, and that in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, be like him in <hi>holineſſe. Ariſtotle</hi> in ranking the morall vertues, gives the precedency unto <hi>Magnanimity;</hi> but the Scripture, in ſetting forth the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of a Magiſtrate, puts holineſſe as the firſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 21. as being a Robe both of the greateſt beauty &amp; neceſſity. Without holineſſe you may be Judges on Earth, but you can never be without it Judges in Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. And what comfort can this be to any, to ſit here upon the <hi>bench</hi> of Judicature, and hereafter to ſtand trembling at Gods <hi>barre?</hi> to be here a <hi>Judge</hi> for a few daies, and afterwards to be an eternall <hi>priſoner?</hi> to weare here a <hi>Chain of gold</hi> as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115733:21"/> an ornament, and hereafter to be bound with the <hi>chaines of darkneſſe</hi> for ever? O therefore, if you would not have your glory and honour to expire in ſo ſhamefull a period, let holineſſe ſhine forth both in your perſons and office.</p>
            <p>Firſt, be holy in your <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>families.</hi> Let not your dwellings be ſtained with open prophaneneſſe in thoſe that are your followers, and filled many times with more diſorder then Tavernes themſelves, having more oathes ſworn in them in one day, then there are prayers made in a whole yeer: having plenty of <hi>healths</hi> drunk in <hi>bowls</hi> of Wine, but no ſweet <hi>odours</hi> offered to God in <hi>Golden vials,</hi> which are Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices more meet for Chriſtians, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 8. Theſe, and ſuch like things, they are a reproach to any family where they be found; but much more to the family of a Magiſtrate, and make their ſinnes to be of a deeper die then their Scarlet with which they are cloathed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, exerciſe holineſſe in your <hi>office,</hi> by preferring the dignity and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115733:21"/> eſteem of thoſe things upon which God hath ſet an eminent mark and character of ſanctity, that they may have that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance and reverence which is due unto them. And here give me leave to inſtance in three particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, be carefull that the holy name of God be not polluted by wicked miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, and Atheiſticall Ruſſians that ſcorn to uſe it in prayer, and yet ſpare not to rend and teare it by helliſh and fiery execrations, and to ſet it as a ſeale to ratifie the worſt of lyes and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods. Late Statutes have raiſed the penalty of ſwearing; but yet oathes are as cheap as ever. And from whence comes all this, but from the negligence and lukewarmneſſe of Magiſtrates that have no zeale to ſtop the growth of ſo foule and ſpreading a ſinne?</p>
            <p>Secondly, doe you that are called Gods, improve your power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the ſolemne ſanctification of Gods day: the beauty and luſtre of which hath of late been more impaired then ever, both by corrupt opinions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115733:22"/> and practiſes. It was wont to be <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> glory that it did excell other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in a religious obſervance of the Lords day; but now it is to be feared that the open contempt and neglect of this day will become both its ſhame and ruine, being for Apoſtacy from what it hath profeſſed branded by the world, and ſeverely puniſhed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhew forth a holy <hi>zeale</hi> in defending and preſerving the life of Religion, and the light of the Goſpel; both which are in greater jeopardy to be deſtroyed then ever they were ſince their firſt plantation amongſt us. For when had <hi>Antichriſt</hi> greater hopes of bringing us back again into <hi>Babylon,</hi> then at preſent? Are not all lawes laid aſleep, which were as ſo many bridles in the jawes of Popiſh <hi>Emiſſaries,</hi> who now like the wicked walk up and down on every ſide? Have we now any <hi>Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth</hi> that may diſtinguiſh a <hi>Gileadite</hi> from an <hi>Ephramite,</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> from a <hi>Recuſant?</hi> Are not all diviſions and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115733:22"/> differences both ſpread and fomented by their artifices, that they may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſcandalize our Religion, and enſnare ſuch as are weak in the faith, by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the unity of their Church, though it hath more rents and patches in it then a beggars coat? Is not the vigilancy of the Locuſts that are amongſt us greater then ever? and the ſpirit of ſlumber which is fallen upon us, deeper then ever? Who is it that obſerves how many of our green and pleaſant things are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten up by them, and how few are left? Surely unleſſe by your wiſdome and courage ſome means be thought upon, and ſet on foot, that may like a ſtrong Weſt wind take away theſe vermine, and caſt them into their <hi>Tyber</hi> from whence they came: I may truly ſay, there is but a ſtep between Ruine and this ancient City.</p>
            <p>Secondly, be ye who are Gods, like God in the exerciſe of <hi>Juſtice</hi> without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, and reſpect of perſons: ſo as not to weigh the poore mans cauſe by the ballance of the <hi>law,</hi> and the rich mans
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115733:23"/> cauſe by the ballance of <hi>favour</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: to be a hatefull <hi>tyrant</hi> to the one, and a ſhamefull <hi>flatterer</hi> to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Silkworm</hi> in the Fable, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to the <hi>Spider,</hi> that the threads which ſhe ſpun, did captivate Nobles and great ones; but the web which the Spider made, did ſerve onely to catch Flies. And ſuch ſhould be the lawes, and the execution of them by Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, which have ſtrength and power in them to take hold of great men, when offenders, as well as of the poore, who uſually moſt feele the ſmart of them. What honour is it for a Judge, to ſtock, to whip, to mulct a malefactor that is poore and friendleſſe, and to court with civilities a <hi>Right worſhipfull</hi> ſwearer or drunkard? to be full of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives againſt the one, and to be mute before the other? Is this to fulfill the office of a Magiſtrate, who by his oath is bound to doe juſtice without feare, and without favour? I have read, that in <hi>Juſtinians</hi> time the Oath of the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges had dreadfull imprecations annexed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115733:23"/> unto it, whereby they did wiſh unto themſelves, that if they did not do right unto every one, the <hi>trembling</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi> the <hi>leproſie</hi> of <hi>Gehazi,</hi> the <hi>lot</hi> of <hi>Judas</hi> might befall them. Though there be no ſuch bitter ingredients put into your Oath, that might make it to be like the water of jealouſie; yet let me tell you, that God can inflict upon cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Magiſtrates judgements that may be parallel to theſe. He can by letting his dread fall upon them, make the joynts of their loynes to be looſed, and their knees to ſmite one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: He can cauſe a leproſie to cleave to their eſtate, which ſhall make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean both to them; and their poſterity. He can, by filling their conſciences with horror and deſpaire, make them to ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>My ſoule chooſeth ſtrangling and death, rather then life.</hi> And therefore be wiſe, O ye Rulers, and conſider often what comfortable anſwer your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences can make to that queſtion of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Doe ye indeed ſpeak righteouſneſſe, O congregation? doe ye judge uprightly,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115733:24"/> O ye ſonnes of men?</hi> Pſal. 58. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, be like unto God in <hi>wiſdom</hi> and mature deliberation, that ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and precipitancy may not blemiſh the ſentence and decree which you paſs, nor make others to cry out, that their cauſe is judged, but not examined. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> in the Emblem is repreſented with a <hi>ballance</hi> in the one hand, and a <hi>ſword</hi> in the other; and firſt, matters muſt be weighed by it, that ſo it may be ſeen on which ſide truth lies, before an equall ſentence and judgement can be paſſed. He that uſeth onely the ſword, and not the ballance, may ſmite an innocent <hi>Naboth,</hi> and acquit a guilty <hi>Ahab.</hi> A Judge, though he is to be <hi>Coecus in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendo,</hi> blind in the impartiall execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the law; yet is he to be <hi>Oculatus in dijudicando,</hi> eagle-ey'd in the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny and diſquiſition of all matters that come before him, whether <hi>judiciall</hi> or <hi>criminall.</hi> Though he is not to know any perſons, yet he is to know and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand every cauſe; and to be more circumſpect, in regard that truth oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115733:24"/> ſtands like a little marke in a wide field, which cannot be eaſily diſcerned; eſpecially when it is hid by the falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations of a malicious <hi>informer.</hi> Thus <hi>David</hi> was ſlandered by wicked <hi>Doeg,</hi> unto <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 22. 10. Or when it is diſguiſed by the arts and inſinuations of <hi>the Advocate;</hi> and thus <hi>Paul</hi> was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented to <hi>Foelix</hi> by <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 5. Or when it is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the want of <hi>evidence</hi> and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to give light unto it: and thus it was in that eager contention between the two mothers for the living childe, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. 22. Now in theſe difficulties, if the eye of wiſdome in a Magiſtrate ſhould not be awake to diſcern; if pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould not be more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to direct, how quickly might judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be turned into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe into hemlock? how ſoon might the ſword of juſtice be ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the blood of innocency, by having the edge of it turned upon the righteous, and the back of it towards the wicked? Doe you therefore who are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115733:25"/> in Authority, and ſit in the high places of Judicature, make the prayer of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> when he was called to the Throne of his father, to be frequently yours, in asking of God <hi>an underſtanding heart to judge his people, that you may diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and bad, 1 King.</hi> 3. 9. And make the practice of <hi>Job</hi> your conſtant pattern, to <hi>ſearch out the cauſe</hi> which you know not, <hi>Job</hi> 29. 16.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, be like God in <hi>mercy,</hi> who is by the Apoſtle repreſented unto us both as a <hi>Father,</hi> and as a <hi>Judge,</hi> in one and the ſame verſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17. All whoſe waies are by the Prophet ſaid to be <hi>mercy and truth, Pſal.</hi> 25. 10. He hath not one path of truth, and another of mercy; but they are both enterchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably woven and twiſted one within a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and thereby are made a mutual foile to ſet off each others beauty. In the higheſt manifeſtation of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon ſinne, in which it and mercy did ſeem to be at an irreconcileable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, his wiſdome found out a way for righteouſneſſe and peace to meet and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115733:25"/> kiſſe each other; by making his Sonne a <hi>Suerty</hi> to ſuffer puniſhment for mans ſinne, and an <hi>Head</hi> to ſanctifie his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to reſtore to him his image. It ſhould therefore be the greateſt care of thoſe who are called Gods on earth, to preſerve the unity &amp; concord of juſtice and mercy in the exerciſe of their office, as the two faireſt Jewels that doe moſt adorn Authority; as the two ſtrongeſt pillars that doe beſt ſupport it, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it upon the ſureſt Baſis. <hi>The Throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe. Prov. 16. 12. The Throne is upholden by mercy. Prov. 20. 28.</hi> Juſtice without mercy turns into rigour, and ſo becomes hatefull; mercy without juſtice turns into fond pitty, and ſo becomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. As then the Rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Pot of Manna were by Gods command laid up in the ſame Ark: ſo let Mercy and Juſtice be both preſerved entire in the boſome of the ſame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; And the one will render his Authority awfull; and the other will make it amiable &amp; full of complacency.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115733:26"/>
            <p>And now to move you to demeane and carry your felves as ſo many living pictures of the great God, and to make his excellencies to ſhine in the righteous adminiſtration of your Office, I ſhall briefly propound two arguments which the Text in two words doth ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>God ſtands in the congregation.</hi> The Ethiopians were anciently wont to ſet an empty chair in the midſt of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment place, to put them in mind that God was preſent among them, as <hi>Lori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> reports. Others ſay twelve, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that the Angels were ſpectators of them. But you need no ſuch ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to quicken you to the doing of righteous things. The <hi>memento</hi> in the Text, that <hi>God ſtandeth in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods,</hi> duely thought upon, and believed, cannot but be more prevalent then all other Remembrances what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. What ſouldier is there that will be a Coward in the preſence of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall? What ſervant is there that will be a loiterer under the eye of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? And what Magiſtrate is there that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115733:26"/> will or can be corrupt, that believes God to ſtand at his right hand? Will he not ſay with <hi>Joſeph, how can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt God?</hi> Gen. 39. 9. will he not ſay with <hi>Job, what then ſhall I doe when God riſeth up? and when he viſiteth, what ſhall I anſwer him?</hi> Job 31. 13.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God <hi>judgeth the Gods</hi> themſelves. Though you here ſit upon <hi>Thrones,</hi> yet you muſt ere long ſtand at his <hi>Tribunal,</hi> and be openly judged in the ſight of Angels and men. Though now you weigh and ſcan the actions of others by your beam, yet you muſt be weighed by the ballance of heaven, and woe unto you if you be found too light. God weighed <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in the midſt of his cups, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 27. And ſo he may doe you in the midſt of your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and tyrannie. And the greater your ſinnes be, the lighter you will be in the ſcale of divine juſtice; but the heavier will be your condemnation. God weighed the rich man in the midſt of his ſecurity, and while he promiſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115733:27"/> himſelfe the reſt of many yeares, that night he required his ſoule of him, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 20. And ſo he may deale with you while you bleſſe your ſelves in your heart, ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imaginations of my heart, and adde one iniquity to another. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 19, 20. If therefore there be any whoſe conſciences tell them, that though they ſit in the Aſſembly of the Gods, they yet doe things moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their name and office, Let them conſider, that he who judgeth without reſpect of perſons muſt be their Judge, whoſe ſentence they cannot fly, whoſe wrath they cannot beare. And this ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing thought (if any thing) will make <hi>Daniels</hi> counſel to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> to be moſt acceptable to them, <hi>To break off their ſinnes by righteouſneſse, and their iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poore; if it may be a lengthning of their tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Dan.</hi> 4. 27.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 22. line 7. <hi>for</hi> affected, <hi>read</hi> effected. p. 29. l. 8. <hi>for</hi> duſt, <hi>r.</hi> dull.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
